software engineering radio episode 57
compile-time metaprogramming with
converge
[Music]
welcome listeners thanks for once again
tuning in to software engineering radio
this episode is on compile-time
metaprogramming or creating
domain-specific languages through syntax
extension in order to talk about this
rather non-mainstream topic we have a
guest our guest today is Lawrence Trat
he's a research fellow at the department
of computer science at King's College in
London and he's co-lead of their
software and systems modeling team he is
also the creator and inventor basically
of the converged programming language
this language implements the concepts
we're going to talk about in this
session this is once again a session
about language design with a specific
focus on two main specific languages
it's going to be very interesting have
fun and again we recorded this episode
at the Cho conference 2006 in Denmark
and Aarhus and yeah have fun welcome our
guest Lawrence tret welcome thank you
very much so we were talking today about
a fancy title dsl implementation a
compile-time by a syntax extension and
also maybe another title could be
compiler metaprogramming yes you could
say that you could also simplify it
somewhat if you wanted to just saying
macros as an academic we like to choose
ridiculously long titles and also there
are probably differences with regards to
macros as we know them as in C++ or C
and we'll talk about that in a moment
so I mean we've talked in previous
episodes about ESL's so we probably
don't have to fill people in about what
a DSL is but if you could give us your
interpretation of what you think these
are important for and why you chose to
implement these else the way you do it
and and maybe also explaining in as an
overview what the way actually is you
choose to implement yourself okay well I
think the term domain-specific languages
is being around for a very very long
time and I think that it
kind of being forgotten at various
stages what's interesting is that we're
going through a resurgence and use of
the term and if you go out to the
developer on the street and say DSL one
of the things you're going to get back a
lot now is talking about the use of Ruby
the way that they're doing these little
in sort of inline dsls some function
calls using some of the little block
structures they have to get things going
I think that's a perfectly valid use of
DSL however I don't think that it's
necessarily using the concept to its
fullest potential so what I would like
to see with DSL is people using some
fairly rich languages new languages new
syntax to express things that they were
very difficult to express before so it's
more than just hacking around a little
bit with some programming language stuff
that you already have it's very much
about creating something new allowing
you something that you couldn't do
easily before and that's primarily
syntactically something different or I
think that if you want people to have a
good chance of expressing something very
useful that they couldn't do before it
does involve new syntax yeah I mean the
Ruby folks and we'll talk to Obi
Fernandes about this stuff in a
subsequent episode that if you'd have
embedded syntax in our embedded DSL in
Ruby the freedom you have for adapting a
syntax is limited and I guess that's one
of the focus points where you think you
try to do better that yes absolutely and
I think what they're doing is they're
making very good use of things they
already had but of course that only gets
you so far and that may be all you need
but if you restrict yourself to that
you're very much constraining the
possible universe of things that you can
express okay so if we try to go back to
what a DSL actually is I think you have
this nice paraphrase stuff from this guy
called who doc I don't didn't know him
personally or actually didn't know his
name so does it make sense to briefly go
over this characteristics of DSL and
then shall we or disagree yeah I think
it's a very good thing so my thinking
behind this is although the term DSL or
maybe not the always the term but the
concepts have been around for a long
time
there's some very nice pair of papers
from 1996 from a chap called Paul hew
dak and I apologize if I pronounced his
surname wrong I've never met an Ivan
from the University of Yale and what he
did at that point was nailed down what
it is that's interesting about dsls some
of the relevant issues and some very
high-level points so maybe I can go over
those I think they're playful one of the
things he's saying is that a outlining
what a DSL should be and here's several
points I think the ones are the most
relevant is he's saying the DSL is an
abstraction relevant to a specific
domain in other words you take a
particular problem and you say well
here's how I can express it in a normal
programming language you know I have to
do this function calling this function
call that's very low level how can I
move it up a level then you have a DSL
he also said dear cells need to lead to
demonstrable increase in productivity in
a sense that if you'd still takes you as
long to do what you wanted to do as you
could do before you haven't really
gained anything you have to get
something useful in productivity from
using a DSL for it to be useful it's
also basically saying that you want to
try and make it no more difficult than
using a normal programming language in
fact if you're lucky you might be able
to make things more accessible than a
normal programming language is the idea
of having non-programmers program and
program using a DSL at least that's kind
of that you know the Holy Grail yes
that's the probably unachievable yeah
well in the end I think you have to be
realistic about these things but that
the more that you can lower the barrier
to entry is a good thing and I think the
final aim that Hudak outlines is that
people who are using DSL they need to be
able to write their solutions in the DSL
fairly easily and they need to be able
to maintain them well that's something
rather critical you don't want to write
a DSL on Friday afternoon in the office
come back in on Monday and think what
the hell does this do you know I don't
can't understand what I've written so
and you're kind of advertising the idea
of integrating DSL into a host language
which is just for our listeners a
different approach compared to what we
talked about in our model term
development episodes and it's comparable
to
what the Ruby folks do so why do you
think it's it's useful and important to
embed it in a host language and and what
are suitable host languages okay this is
a very good question I think the reason
that you want to embed things in a host
language is the alternative is making a
standalone DSL and to me the best
example of that is make most people are
going to be familiar with make I guess
they listen to this yeah makers are
great is a great tool I still leaves it
and I'm old-fashioned but it's also very
complicated it has its own grammar so
someone somewhere some poor person has
implemented very complex tool they've
gone away and created a grammar using
Lex and yak they have you can always
view makers a sort of little virtual
machine in a sense for make files it's a
complex standalone application and you
can't reuse any of it and it has to have
all the support you know error handling
reading in files all this thing at a low
level so I think the reason you one
would like to embed to yourselves in a
programming language is maybe we can get
some of this low-level stuff that's not
really relevant to the problem we're
trying to do maybe we can get the host
language to do it for us expressions
could be kind of an obvious candidate
for that yes and also you hopefully will
get simple things like simpler
input/output you be able to maybe use
things like the error messages there's a
whole host of things that you hopefully
pick up for free now exactly what you
consider to be a good host language is
dependent on opinion so Hudak for
example thought that everything should
forcibly be in Haskell and although I
have nothing personally again Pascal I'd
not sure this is an entirely realistic
thing to expect of people so I think
that the sort of host languages that you
need as a bare minimum they have to be
very flexible host languages now I also
furthermore believe that really that
means you need to be able to extend
their syntax so the fact that the
language like a ruby thing is a very
flexible language like a Python it's not
quite the same thing as a sort of a lisp
like language perhaps which suddenly you
can start extending it in ways the
original designers never thought of
that's maybe because the Lisp language
basically has no syntax so it's easy to
extend it by you know not at
you know I mean just it's trees
absolutely yep
so Lisp is not a good candidate because
no one's going to use it and it's so
minimalistic that you can do anything
you want with it but it doesn't give you
enough at the beginning to start with
yeah so that's a non-starter so what
you're really looking for is is sort of
a mix I think of what I would call a
modern programming language you know
something that looks like a a Python a
ruby a Java or even a C++ whatever you
consider that a normal developer will be
comfortable with with some of this
flexibility that goes back to the Lisp
sort of days so what you did then is
kind of to invent your own language
called converge or converge I guess
you'll talk about it in a minute and I'm
specifically this language supports as I
understood a macro system that supports
their self so I think it's worth talking
about this one okay so converge is a
language a new language
it looks initially a lot like Python to
people I think that's what people will
first notice about it looks like Python
has been a bit disguised by somebody and
then on top of that it has this compile
time meta programming stuff now compile
time meta programming is a very unwieldy
term that basically means it as a macro
system and the macro system thing that
it has is very heavily influenced by
that in template Haskell so for anyone
who thinks that I'm maybe bashing
Haskell earlier there is some genuinely
good ideas that one can pluck from these
languages and so what converge has is
three language features it needs to
integrate a compile-time meta
programming facility into it you have to
have a macro call now that's a very
standard and easy thing goes all the way
back to Lisp and then the next thing
that it has is something that has
stopped any language since Lisp having a
decent macro system effectively and that
is you need to be able to build up
abstract syntax trees so let me just
pedal back one step to make sure we
don't lose our listeners the idea of of
compartiment our programming is
basically that you have a way of adding
source code to the program that is not
evaluated at runtime but rather during
the compilation process and the result
of evaluating this piece of source code
is a
extry that is then integrated into what
into the byte or machine code that the
compiler creates right yes absolutely so
the trick is with this compiler
metaprogramming is you're interacting
with the compiler the compiled compiler
goes around compiling a file much as a
normal compiler does and it hits
something it's called a splice in
converge but you can just call it a
macro calls that's fine and when it hits
one of those is all and it effectively
evaluates that expression at compile
time and that expression has to return
an abstract syntax tree which is
basically an object object graph yeah
representing some code and that's
relatively well known how to do the
there's this macro call this splice
thing and converge does some has some
neat little tricks that actually make it
rather easier to use than even say
something like template Haskell but it's
fundamentally a relatively well solved
problem the trick is how you make these
abstract syntax trees yep and then just
to again to relate this tool for example
see macros it's been different because a
see macro is evaluated on source level
so it returns kind of a piece of text
that is replaced with a macro call right
so yes I mean a see macro system and I
happen to enjoy see macros because
they're kind of fun in their own weird
twisted little way but they're very much
a double-barrelled shotgun and you can't
really control and when you pull the
trigger the bullet can go anywhere
yeah that's not typing normal checking
it's basically just text expansion and
really as the see macro system you can
use it with any language the C
preprocessor doesn't really know
anything much about C at all the point
of these more advanced macro systems is
they're very well integrated into the
language they can make certain safety
guarantees that for example in a C like
macro system or any templating type
thing like that you've got the chance of
variables from two different things
conflicting with each other and the
preprocessor in C can make no guarantees
about that it people go through all
sorts of Hoops adding extra brackets and
yeah crossing their fingers nothing goes
wrong whereas in converge you love this
stuff is handled for you don't have to
worry about well you don't have to worry
as much about
shooting yourself in the foot now one of
the tricks of Convergys then I guess
that you can program the code that
creates the ast in the same language as
you know also in converge right yes so
it's a completely homogeneous
environment right yeah so you during the
compilation you probably actually run
some kind of virtual machine that
interprets the stuff and the so the
converged compiler is written in
converge so the compiler is running in
the virtual machine so when it comes
across one of these little splice things
it's just temporarily compiles a
temporary module and injects that in the
virtual machine it's running in anyway
so there's a complete interaction
between the compiler and the splice code
and that's rather important because it
allows the user code to interact with
the compiler get it to do things in its
behalf ask your questions and that sort
of thing mm-hm okay so in addition to
the splice construct I think there are
two others one is the quasi quote and
the other is the insertion can you
explain them briefly and then we'll go
on and show how they fit together
well quasi quote sees and that this name
I'm not quite sure how they came up with
it is from the template a scale people
is the mechanism that allows you to
build abstract syntax trees and and the
way it does it is incredibly intuitive
they solved a problem that no one had
solved since Lisp and what what you do
is you surround a normal expression that
you write in the program language with
some funny brackets it's a square
bracket in a vertical bracket at either
side and so you have an expression like
two plus three surrounded by these funny
brackets and that evaluates to some
objects which are the abstract syntax
tree so in that case the outermost
object is going to be a plus object on
the left-hand side will say integer and
then it will say two and on the
right-hand side it was a integer at
three and so suddenly you can create
these very abstract things they're
called abstract syntax trees
unsurprisingly using the normal concrete
syntax that you're familiar with
instead of writing code that has a new
ast node blah-blah-blah-blah plus add
child new ast node integer blahblah
you've hit the nail on the head as to
why these systems have always failed
horribly before because that is a
completely unscalable approach
absolutely yeah that's also just to
divert briefly this is the reason why in
model-driven development you don't use a
model to model transformation to create
source code because that would go back
to creating instances of the source
nodes or
laughter code notes kind of of the ast
of the target language that's just
horrible yes absolutely
and so finally there's this the third
feature is by far the least complicated
it's called insertion in converge it's
called something rather different in
template a scale and basically it allows
you to merge a steves together so you
can build a STS up in chunks and then
nicely and using the normal syntax merge
these things together okay so that
allows us basically to to to heck the
stuff the compiler does by modifying the
output the ast it creates based on code
that looks just like the other code in
our source code but that's not yet DSL
right so so where does how does this
relate to what else is there in converge
to to make it a DSL friendly language
and how does it look like yeah yeah
you're very much right in saying that
that's not all that you need for da
cells and in fact I think what's worth
thinking about here is why would other
languages have have one of these macro
facilities well let's pass one because
it doesn't have anything enough built in
nice to have a macro language to try and
build you extra complex things on top si
has one because C is a very annoying
language to program in you have to have
this preprocessor to make it at least
some more palatable the compile time
metaprogramming converge on its own it's
a fairly rich language it has all the
things that you expect so
really it's all put there to enable dsls
and it turns out that to have DSL
support that is where you can have a
little bit of your source code that's a
completely arbitrary syntax of your
choosing you need one extra language
feature and that's called the DSL block
and it looks rather like a splice a
normal splice in the compile time at
programming sense and that single
feature allows you which is really only
about ten lines of code in the compiler
it's a very simple layer on top suddenly
allows you to embed these completely
alien-looking things and make the whole
facility underneath worthwhile so you
say that there is this piece of convert
code and then there is some kind of
marker that defines what kind of T is
just like maybe an HTML where you have
the script and then type equals
JavaScript or something and then there
is this other code and and the trick
then is
that this code is processed your own
compilation it's pretty much the same
thing
obviously there's a lot more to this
than there is in the example you outline
I will talk about in a minute but the
principle is the same
okay let's let's talk about an example
and the example you talked about in the
talk this morning and again we're
recording this at the Joe conference in
Denmark in October
what is it 2006 the example you showed
there is a time table something to
describe train time train timetables
there so what do you have to do as a dsl
developer notice it here's our user as a
guy who extends the compiler what we
have to do to make this work okay
well the first thing that you have to be
aware is that DSL blocks this DSL input
that the use of writes is just really a
random string the compiler doesn't know
anything about it so if the DSL
implementation author the person
defining the DSL you have to do several
things the first obviously is you have
to design a language of some sort
because the input must be coming in to a
format that you have told the user to
conform to so grammar definition or what
probably it's a free country you can do
it however you want I want very much
suggest that you do it in a traditional
way where you define a grammar and pass
it and then you get a parse tree and you
write a little translator thing that
takes in a pass tree and returns a
converge abstract syntax tree so can you
maybe just what are not so language
savvy listener subset explain the
difference between a parse tree and a
language and ast I can indeed so passing
is a very fun activity but one that's
shrouded in mystery and it actually
could be much simpler than it often
appears basically it's a two-stage
process the first thing that happens is
you take your input and you tokenize
it'll exit depending on how you like to
call it and all that's doing is
splitting it up into words so it's like
taking a random European language and
saying well whenever I see a space that
delimits two words and a full-stop
similarly then you take all these words
that you've tokenized
and then you try and actually make sense
of them in terms of the grammar so if
you make a natural language example you
try to say okay what's the
in my sentence what's a the nouns and so
on and then you're trying to make a tree
structure out of that that allows you to
determine how the sentence that's come
in is structured but at this point all
you've done is determined what the users
told you so that's the parse tree that's
the pass tree and then you're converting
that however you want and into the
abstract syntax tree and there may be a
very close relation between the two but
you your translation you're effectively
writing a mini compiler right and and
and that the abstract syntax tree is
basically an instance of the has to be
in terms of the host language right so
you're converting your domain-specific
language syntax parse tree into a set of
constructs objects instances of AST
types of the host language of converge
yes if it's easier to think of you can
think of it I think without objects you
can imagine it just as a textual
templating approach if you think of a
yeah a sort of model to text translation
here actively the abstract syntax tree
is like the template text but you don't
you don't you don't do it with templates
you actually in fact technically you do
it by instantiate the ast object yes
because you get an awful lot of benefits
that way but that's it's somewhat
sometimes a slightly hard concept to get
hold of yeah so if you move in your mind
from template to text and nice objects
that do lots of other things for you
then you're on the right path okay
one thing I'd like to talk about before
we move on in how to implement a dsl
obviously that should have become clear
by now we're talking about textual
yourselves there is no way of
integrating some graphical notation
because the editor won't make that you
could maybe do some s key art and why
not maybe for tables so what about
parsing do I have to ride my own parcel
to build the parse tree
okay so parsing is one of these things I
think I said earlier it was absolutely
shrouded in mystery it goes back to the
the fact that it's in the mid-1960s that
the theoretical computer science people
already started looking and thinking
well we know we're doing a lot of this
programming stuff now we have different
programming languages how are we going
to make sense of this how are we going
to come up with nice ways of
understanding what the user has told us
and of course computers at the time we
run credit
slow so they invented some very limited
algorithms that can't pass a lot of
languages it would be a bit like saying
I have a way of passing natural language
it works very well for luxembourgish
analytic add predicate object
complexities and it's not gonna work for
English or French or German and you
think well that's not entirely useful is
it it's very limited and we're actually
still stuck with this today so people
have a very negative opinion of passing
because we're stuck with weird terms
like L R LLL ALR none of these terms we
should be forced to know they really
just tell us about the limitations of
the underlying algorithm the good news
that some not that well known so I hope
that I'm spreading the you know the good
news gospel here is that there are much
better are algorithms out there that
allow you to pass any context-free
grammar and any sane programming
language and C++ is excluded from this
is context-free which means you can pass
nearly anything that you can imagine so
if you're a dsl author what you have to
do is say ok there's a passing algorithm
built-in to convert it's called an early
past it can do anything that I want
really I just have to write a little
simple grammar definition and unlike
using Lex and yak or Java CC or those
are the things I can write it in a way
that makes sense to me as a human and
I'm not subject to the whims of the
passing algorithm so you said before
that the user has to come up with some
way of transforming the string into a
parse tree and then in an AST but you
basically what you say is that there
isn't built-in library that helps you do
this if you provide an early grammar and
then you get all the magic so that the
function to implement that the peers are
parsing is a couple of lines calling the
library I guess absolutely it's one of
the fundamental philosophies that I've
had when creating converge is that da
cells follow a fairly standard set
sequence of steps and one of those is
every DSL every sensible DSL is going to
pass some text get a pass tree and then
translate that so why not have a single
function that takes this in a return to
parse tree and that's exactly what there
is there you when you write one of these
little DSL implementation functions that
the
takes in a DSL block basically the
handle of function for a particular kind
of syntax yes exactly it you say okay
well here's I'm gonna hand off to
another function here's the input I got
from the user here's a grammar and
here's some extra keywords and maybe I
need to know about and that's it please
give me back a parse tree and it does so
that the menu will work tedious parsing
stuff it's gone away and then the
grammars you need to write are basically
some kind of a B and F like thing where
you define keywords and and tokens yeah
it's a fairly standard ebn F type thing
of course is going back to what I said
earlier it's it's a pure rebn F in the
sense that it's not like a yak sort of
thing where if anyone has ever had the
misfortune to use yak you write what
looks like a perfectly BNF notation you
run it through yak misses shift reduce
error the hell is a shift would you say
why do I care about that none of that
sort of stuff you just put in your
normal evening F notation and it does it
yeah but you don't add any side effect
declarations or you know this stuff you
do this in a separate function that's
actually the transformation from the
parse tree to the ast more so in a lot
of passing tools as the passing
algorithm is is passing a text you are
also doing side actions right a lot of
those are because of the sort of
limitations of a gain of machines forty
years ago where they couldn't hold
things in memory nowadays it's much
easier to pass the whole text and get it
all up the whole thing
exactly build a whole tree and in
converge those represented is nice
simple lists and then to go over that
fully created tree and do things then
and that makes a lot of things an awful
lot easier it's kind of like sex whereas
Dom Indian XML processing kind of this
is very much a Dom view of the world
right a sax for you the world yes so and
then you you write probably functions
that transform the the parse tree
elements into objects in the in the in
the ast and I know obviously you write
these functions in in conversions yes
and probably the nice thing is that
there you probably then use the splicing
stuff to actually create the objects for
the ast exactly quite nice yes so again
this is very much this idea of an a
modulus environment that a translator is
I
use the word translator cuz I don't
necessarily like to use the term mini
compiler it frightens people but really
really all that it is but a lot of the
hard work is taken out of it it's not
frightening like compilers up and
converge gives you in very very simple
framework and basically you write one
function per rule in your grammar and
that takes in a little bit of a pass
tree and as you said creates the objects
for an abstract syntax tree and you're
just using those three compiled so
metaprogramming features we talked about
earlier the splice the quasi quote in
the insertion that's it everything is
built out of those
ok so let's shift gears a little bit and
talk about error reporting this is an
interesting topic because some of you
listeners might have heard about using
C++ templates for compiler meta
programming which first of all it looks
awful and second one thing that is
really cool about it if you do something
wrong you get those error messages with
you know where an error message is like
25,000 characters long because some
identifier has been built up through
concatenating the recursive template
evaluations so that's a big problem
so one thing you have talked about in
your presentation is that error
reporting is something you've
specifically taken care of in converge
and I think that's worth talking about
yeah well it was one of those things I
mean it's obvious in a sense that error
reporting is important no one is in the
right mind is gonna say it's not there
but I mean when I delivered the first
version of converge it had some new
nice-ish error reporting things but it
just didn't seem enough and what became
clear to me is that both the person who
writes the DSL the implementation author
and to people who use it require good
error reporting and generally neither
side got good error reporting at best
maybe one or the other did I don't throw
those systems were few and far between
so it became very clear to me that if
you want to write a good DSL well even
if it's good it's still gonna have
problems and I've never written an
error-free line of code yet in my life
and I don't suspect there are many
people out there you have so you've got
to come up with a way that you can
report errors to both the implementation
author and the user and that is
particularly tricky because if you
consider for example against C macros if
the compile
reports on error then of course the
error is reported based on the code that
is there after the macro has been
expanded but if the developer looks into
the source code of course the macro is
there so it's very hard to actually find
out what's happening and I guess it's
kind of the same problem here because
the error is reported based on the
abstract syntax tree that has been
created from the transformation instead
of what the DSL input was like well
that's one of the things that I set out
to tackle and I think that I've come up
with a solution that seems to be very
neat and seems to tackle the whole
problem as it were so the basic
philosophy is this there's a concept in
converge and it doesn't really matter
what it's called called a source info
and basically it tracks the location of
some source code from the point that
it's passed until the point that it's
converted into a bytecode instruction
run in the virtual machine someone like
the traceability stuff the MDA folks
talked about yes it is very similar to
that but it's very different than the
way that these things are normally done
in program languages normal program
languages if an error happens at runtime
you get a little report saying at line
such-and-such this error occurred but
there's very much the idea that each
error is just associated with one line
yep in converge the because when an
error happens it might be related either
to the user's DSL input or the
translation that the DSL implementation
author created error reports can be
associated with more than one source
location so you can get an error and it
says well I got to this point in the
stack frame and this is associated with
two source code points or three or four
because you can layer dia cells and then
if you're a DSL user you can alert DSL
that means you can embed dear Zeldin
above the adults you can indeed nice so
that means again you have to take a
dramatically different approach because
if error reporting was just based on
reporting some weird part of a C++
compiler string concatenation well you
won't even be able to work out which
layer of your embedded DSL the thing
occurred in let alone any more details
so here the error report comes back and
says well the error is related to the
third line in your DSL input as a user
and in this line in converged source
code which was the translation class
that both the you
at the DSL and the implementation all
the contract down the error and work out
which one of them is responsible
another thing that's maybe interesting
is that you talked about before that
having ESL's integrated into a host
language is particularly useful because
you can reuse parts of the host language
and one specific aspects probably the
expression language so am i right there
you are very right because one of the
things that again going back to this
nice chat mr. Hudak noticed is that dsl
x' always tend to evolve their
requirements and one of the things that
he put his finger right on the money
here is that as they evolved they always
tend to evolve features that people who
wanted to get in from programming
languages in other words you stopped the
small dsl and you think i really need a
for loop in here oh then I really need
the if statement and then then something
that looks like a function call they
always start to creat features of that
ilk so if you're going to add in an
expression language you don't want to do
what most ear cells do which is put in a
badly designed one that's been created
from scratch being badly implemented
badly debugged and tends to fall over in
horrible ways yeah so converging allows
you to embed its own expression language
within DSL x' that way you're taking
advantage of the fact that somebody in
this case me it's designed hopefully
design well but that's another issue
designed and implemented and tested and
debugged that thing and in fact you can
add this expression language introduced
hell it's two lines of code for a DSL
invitational --this is suddenly rather
than having to write hundreds and
hundreds of lines of code to make their
own one that's basically a bit crappy
they use someone else's 14 lines of code
so these two lines of code in your DSL
probably grammar or listed in the
Krammer or you say it or does it say you
know you can use any kind of converge
code here or is it only you know you
couldn't use expressions or you can only
use function calls or can you restrict
what you can use from those language you
could in theory embed any part of
convert you wanted yeah in practice I
would very much suggest that you stick
to just embedding the expression
language
fortunately the expression language in
converge includes things like function
definitions because it's an entirely
expression based language so functions
evaluate the function objects that you
can then call and so you could with
you can probably do nearly everything
you're likely to want to do and if
you're particularly masochistic maybe
you can do some other things as well
okay so maybe to to to maybe not yet
directly wrap up but to summarize what
we talked about one thing youyou kind of
emphasize is that you don't just have a
language but rather a kind of little
mini process that kind of suggests
people who free country if you're going
to do what they want but suggest to
people a process of how to build a DSL
and as part of convert yeah I think this
is something that's very important one
of the problems if you do a standalone
DSL you know you go out and make
something that looks a little bit like
the maker program you have to start from
scratch there's no obvious order in
which you need to do things and so the
problem is you have a slightly random
sequence of steps every time you do it
and as we all know when you do a
slightly random sequence of steps the
result might be rather random as well so
converge has a sort of implicit process
as I think of it and the way that it
does it is really there are several
features built-in language to say well
if you do this step then you might as
well do this step next and it really
starts off with the fact as I said
earlier you can use the normal converge
tokenizer to tokenize things now you can
do it write your own tokenizer if you
want but don't try at the point exactly
so if you start with that and then you
write a grammar those that steps one and
two then you write a translation class
and then you test and debug it then you
deploy it and each one follows very
naturally from the other and you don't
have to put a great deal of brainpower
and thinking how am I going to create
this thing that's pretty much mapped out
for you so and deploying means you can
wrap this as a couple library and then
make available to your users or oh well
deployment means whatever you want it to
mean that's the one thing that an S it
doesn't really give you any great handle
with because deployment means you know
shoving things off to different peoples
different is there a way of packaging up
such a DSL definition that there is
because one of the things I haven't
mentioned is converge is a little
unusual if you think it's just a Python
star language it's a bit unusual in that
every single file is compiled to
bytecode file and all those are linked
together into a binary file mm-hm
and obviously it's on a machine code
executable but it could as well be so
you
can just ship that single linked
executable off to somebody and if
they've got the converged virtual
machine the other end they can just run
it okay so you're from a University I
think we didn't talk about that before
and you're from King's College in London
I got that right all right in Houston
with University College and this morning
and University College just seems like
the biggest competitor so has actually
been used or is it a purely research
prototype thing oh it's a it's a very
good question and yes I am from Kings
and the way this started was I was
involved in a research project and we
were working with industry and we were
working in fact all to do with models
UML and so on and we were creating dsls
and we were really in trouble trying to
create these things wrapped rapidly so I
developed all this stuff trying to find
a way around my problem and I kind of
did it in isolation which is the
standard academic way of doing things
and then after I had a semi useful
product I shipped it off to some my
industrial collaborators and they they
looked at it looks like it could be
vague useful they put a couple of people
on and gradually there's been a handful
of people who've been creating real DSL
so I've created a couple of fairly
decent sized ones mostly to do with
model transformations I did a system it
has three interlocking DSL one to do
with making little graphical languages
on model transformations and related one
those were some thousand lines of code
or so not a big system but if you tried
to do that in the traditional DSL
creation method it would be very
difficult and the industrial
collaborators who had Tata Consultancy
Services who funded a lot of this
research have gone off and done some
really interesting DSL work of their own
and of course they're not academics
they've chosen the whole load of very
different things and I however have
thought were practical of doing okay so
before we wrap up do you want to kind of
give us a couple of points of wisdom
that you learned from your ideas are
creating creation experience that people
should consider when building their own
DSL infrastructure it may be except from
just using converge obviously it would
be very nice if people use converging
answer almost guaranteed brewed to
success I think this there's some things
that I've noticed the first thing is
that if you use an approach
convert uses you get some fairly easy to
use tear cells in other words if someone
can program they don't have to know
anything extra to use the DSL the
barrier to entry is very low if you mean
that's from a promote gives other user a
spinal fluid ESO uses this meta cause
it's actin nicely into a generic
programming environment exactly so the
the barrier to using these things is
very low and that's very important
however someone still has to go away and
design these languages and design is a
matter of taste and some people have
good taste some people have bad taste
some people have no taste at all and you
are therefore alone and whoever
implements DSL designing a good language
there's nothing convert or anything else
can do to force good design right yeah
one of the things that we that I think
I've been come particularly aware of is
where the advantage comes in in a DSL
and what's become clear to me is
something that in a sense is very
obvious if you think of textual regular
expressions they're a way of expressing
really complex constraints over text you
know we use them on the command line on
Gretel and Perl or whatever and in a
handful of characters you can express
something that if you had to write a
program would take sometimes pages to
write up and involve horrible things
like backtracking yeah so you get a lot
of the benefit from dsls when a bit of
terse syntax allows you to express
something very complicated yeah that
said if you just add new syntax to your
DSL willy-nilly you end up in all sorts
of problems because it makes the things
rather complicated to use and also once
you've added syntax to language you can
never take syntax away users become very
attached to syntax so it's better to
start off in a cautious fashion I've
realized make the language of small as
possible start small always start small
you can't predict which way these things
were going and also another little
psychological oddity of DSL users if you
give someone a library they may be sayst
like I don't like the name of that
function or some very minor coins but
you don't tend to get that much pushback
when you give someone language they
suddenly feel as if they have the right
to all sorts of opinions and you get
back all sorts of feedback that you have
to take account of so the less you give
them to begin with
the less you end up having to unpick and
you can't predict what they will say
let's think one thing I'm sure
one one point I'd like to touch on
briefly at the end is that the issue of
editor support I mean one reason why
Ruby can be used for embedded dsls is
first of all it is a quite flexible
syntax and second is its it's not very
strongly typed actually it's not at all
statically typed so you don't have the
typical editors with code completion
syntax highlighting and all that stuff
so I guess you you somehow have the same
issue here so if you have a piece of
converge code regular converge code you
might have an MX whatever it's called
configuration to do syntax highlighting
but you can't easily I mean it's
conceivable but it's additional work to
do to actually make their a DSL specific
code completion syntax highlighting
stuff that's not the scope of the
project at this time it's it's certainly
not something that that I I would
personally be able to get involved in
mostly because I'm a very old fashioned
and primitive person and on some days
I'll program in five or six different
programming languages so I use a
bog-standard text editor but I do
understand that people do want this rich
text editing support and I very much
support that code completion is very
nice but in the end this takes us to the
intentional programming folks right with
whom we might talk at some later stage
maybe but I don't know but so they have
this full support including editor
debugger and stuff so what about
debugging in your case and there is no
built-in debugger in converge again I'm
a little bit old-school printer here
printf was given to me and it's done me
ever since I found out about it but I
think going back to the editing issue I
think one of the good things about this
is the barrier to entry is very low if
if say I said to you when you create
your DSL you're also going to have to
tell me how to do completion here then
there are approaches which force that
then you suddenly raise the barrier a
lot could be optional right yeah but one
of the things that converge has going
it's fabled though it is like Ruby a
dynamically typed language it's slightly
more static things like variable
references and module references are
entirely determined at compile type so
actually you can probably make a much
better stab at completion than you can
similar languages and I think if you
design your dsls in the correct fashion
you can make a similar good stab at
those yeah but as you said that's not my
main focus okay okay so there anything
else you want to say at this time well
it's obviously thank you very much the
interview and yeah thank you well
convert is still in its early days yeah
I wouldn't want anyone to bet their
business or their life on it but it is
something I would very much encourage
people to go and have a look at to give
comments I think it's a really nice way
of developing dsls it gives us something
that we didn't really have before very
nice mechanism so please you know feel
free to go to the website and download
the versions it's converge PL dot org
and we'll put this in the show notes
excellent thank you very much thank you
and I think we're going to some party at
the conference now so we wrap this up we
have ten minutes left I'm sure it'll be
a well time thank you
[Music]
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio if you want to get
more information about software
engineering radio or if you want to give
us feedback please go to our website at
se - radio dot net you can also contact
the team at team at SAE - radio dotnet
although we prefer entries in our
comment system on the website so other
people can see what you think
software engineering radio wants to
thank Henning poly for the intro and
outro music as well as Lipson for
providing the bandwidth this episode of
se radio as well as all other episodes
is licensed under Creative Commons
license
see the software engineering radio
website for details